Putin felt
that Russia faced an existential threat.
He had to deal with that threat.
And the United States
and the Europeans were doing
nothing to negotiate a way to avoid war.
The West is leading
Ukraine down the primrose
path, and the Israelis
are executing a genocide in Gaza.
It's not China's fault
that it wants to be powerful.
So if you get into trouble
and you dial 911,
there's nobody at the other end.
Hi, this is John Mearsheimer,
and I'm here today
to make my first video
on my new YouTube channel.
And the subject I'd like to talk about
is the origins of the war in Ukraine.
That war began on February 24th of 2022.
And of course, the war continues on.
Indeed, it's been longer than World
War One.
And I want to talk about its origins.
And in particular,
I'm interested in the question of why
the Russians were not deterred
and why they actually attacked on
February 24th, 2022.
And this is essentially a question
of conventional deterrence, because
the attack was a conventional attack,
nuclear weapons were not involved here.
Nuclear deterrence was not at play.
It's a question
of conventional deterrence.
And again,
why were the Russians not deterred?
Now, this is a very interesting
subject to me
because the war is important,
but also because I actually wrote a book
on conventional deterrence
during the Cold War.
The whole question of whether or not
the Soviet Union
or more generally,
the Warsaw Pact would attack
NATO was an issue of great importance,
and people paid attention to the question
of when or under what circumstances
the Russians might attack against NATO.
And I actually wrote my PhD dissertation
on the subject of conventional deterrence.
And my first book,
which grew out of my dissertation,
is entitled Conventional Deterrence.
So I've thought a lot about this subject.
And because the NATO Warsaw Pact
situation from the Cold War,
Cold War bears
a lot of resemblance
to the Russian decision to invade Ukraine.
I think I have a lot to say, or
I should say, I think my theory has a lot
to say
about the origins of the Ukraine war.
So what I'd like to do today is I'd first
like to lay out my theory
of conventional deterrence.
Leaving aside the whole question
of the Ukraine war, just explain to you
how I think about conventional deterrence.
And then once I finish that task,
switch gears
and talk about the Ukraine war, talk
about what happened on February 24th, 2022
and what has happened
subsequently and in essence, marry
my theory of conventional deterrence
to the Ukraine war.
Now, let me start by talking
about conventional deterrence.
And the first point I want to make,
and this is a terribly important point,
is that when you think about
conventional deterrence, you have to focus
on the political variable
and the military variable.
And you're probably saying to yourself,
what exactly does he mean?
When I talk about the political variable,
it's very,
very important to understand
that there are political forces
that push a state to go to war,
and the question of how powerful
those political forces are really matters
for purposes of understanding deterrence.
So you have this political variable,
and then you have a military variable.
And the military variable is all about how
well you will do
on the battlefield
once you're engaged in the fight
militarily, how likely are you to succeed?
What sorts of costs will you have to pay?
That's
what the military variable is all about.
The political variable deals
with those broader political forces
that are pushing you to contemplate
going to war,
and it's very important to understand
that you have to take into account
both the military
and the political variable.
And this, by the way,
this relationship between politics
and military considerations is reflected
in Clausewitz's very famous dictum
that war is an extension of politics
by other means.
War, meaning the military variable, is
an extension of politics by other means.
So we have to always keep in mind
that there are
these two variables at play,
and we have to think not only about
each variable by itself,
but how they relate to each other.
Now, let me start by talking
about the military variable.
My argument is that when states think
about going to war, and here we're talking
about a large scale conventional war,
you want to keep that in mind.
Remember
I said before, what motivated me to study
this issue was the NATO Warsaw Pact
conventional balance during the Cold War.
And here we're talking
about the balance of power between
Russia's conventional forces
and Ukraine's conventional forces.
Back in February of 2022.
So when a country,
whether it's the Warsaw Pact,
thinking about attacking NATO or Russia,
thinking
about attacking Ukraine
when it thinks about the
military considerations at play,
my argument
is it focuses on the particular strategy
that it might employ to win the war.
And my argument is that a state that's
thinking about attacking another state
in a major conventional war has three
strategies that it can choose among.
What is what I call
blitzkrieg two is what I call attrition
strategy, and three is what I call
a limited Aim strategy.
Now, let me unpack what I mean
when I talk about each one of those
strategies and attrition strategy
and the blitzkrieg strategy
of both aimed
at producing a decisive victory,
a blitzkrieg is designed to produce
a quick and decisive victory.
Think about the Germans
invading France in 1940.
On May 10th, 1940, the Wehrmacht invades
France.
It quickly overruns France
and then pushes the British Army off the
beaches at Dunkirk.
This is a classic blitzkrieg.
Blitzkrieg produce quick and decisive
victories and attrition.
Strategy, in contrast, produces
a slow, a protracted but decisive victory.
So it's important to understand that
with both a blitzkrieg
and an attrition strategy,
you are pursuing decisive victory,
defeating the other side almost,
if not completely.
The third strategy is a limited
aim strategy,
and there a state
does not pursue a decisive victory.
What it does
is it simply conquers territory
in that rival state.
It goes to war and lops off
or conquers
a small piece of the other side's
territory,
and then it moves to a defensive strategy.
This is why it's called a limited
aim strategy,
and not a strategy
that pursues decisive ends,
which is what blitzkrieg
and an attrition strategy do.
So these are the three strategies
that a state can choose among.
Now how do we rank order these strategies?
What are these
three strategies say about the likelihood
of deterrence succeeding or failing?
My argument is that if a state can
launch a blitzkrieg and win.
Let me put it slightly differently.
If a state thinks it can
launch a blitzkrieg,
that will produce a quick and decisive
victory, deterrence will fail.
If it thinks that it has to launch
an attrition strategy.
It can't win quickly.
It's aiming to win decisively,
but it can't win quickly.
Then it will not attack.
So an attrition strategy
promotes deterrence,
and a blitzkrieg strategy promotes
the failure of deterrence.
Just to go to World War Two.
One of the principal reasons
that the Germans invaded
France in May of 1940
was that they had a blitzkrieg strategy,
which they thought would produce a quick
and decisive victory.
And that's why they went to war.
And they were successful
when the Germans invaded the Soviet Union.
A year later, this is on June 22nd, 1941.
They thought that the blitzkrieg strategy
that they had ready to go
would produce a quick and decisive victory
inside the Soviet Union.
Of course, it failed in the Soviet case,
and the war
evolved into a war of attrition.
Very important to understand that
the Germans did not go into the Soviet
Union in 1941, thinking
they would end up in a war of attrition.
If that were the case, I would argue
they would not have attacked.
They attacked because they thought
they had a blitzkrieg strategy
that would provide a war winning strategy.
So you see that blitzkrieg.
Let's create because it
produces or promises
to produce a quick and decisive victory
is a formula for deterrence failure.
And I would argue, by the way,
that during the Cold War, the Soviets
and their Warsaw Pact allies
never gave any thought
of attacking into Western Europe
because they understood
that they could not execute a blitzkrieg
against the NATO forces
that would be arrayed
against them in the fight.
And that's why deterrence was so robust.
This is not to deny, of course,
that nuclear deterrence mattered as well.
Now let's go to the limited Aim strategy.
The limited Aim strategy
is the easiest strategy to execute
because it is limited,
which means that all you're doing
is grabbing some territory
from your adversary.
You're not attempting
to defeat your adversary decisively.
It is a limited strategy.
There are limited aims at play,
so it is the easiest
of the three strategies
to execute for sure.
But actually it is not ultimately
an attractive strategy.
And the reason that it is ultimately not
an attractive strategy is
because you don't defeat the other side
decisively,
and invariably the other side
will continue the fight
and you will end up in a war of attrition.
So it's very important to understand that.
What I'm saying here is that
if you launch a blitzkrieg and it fails,
you'll end up in a war of attrition.
And if you launch a limited Aim strategy,
you'll be successful at first,
but it will probably end up
turning in to a war of attrition.
And nobody wants a war of attrition.
So there is a powerful incentive
to stay away from a limited Aim strategy,
and there's certainly a powerful incentive
to stay away from an attrition strategy.
So when those are the two options
on the table,
you're likely to see deterrence succeed.
It's when an army can launch a blitzkrieg
that deterrence is likely to fail.
So this is my story about
the military variable. Now
as I said earlier,
you have to take into account
the political variable as well.
Now, there's no question that anytime
a country is thinking about going to war,
the political variable
is going to basically say,
we have very good reason to go to war.
By definition, you don't think about
launching an attack against an adversary
unless you think there is a strong set
of political reasons for doing so.
Nevertheless, in some cases,
in some cases,
the intensity of the political forces
that are pushing a state to go to war
are extremely great.
That a state feels that it has
to solve the problem that it faces,
it has to solve the political problem
that it faces with military force.
And what happens in cases like that
is that states
usually go to a limited aim strategy.
This is
this is the the set of cases where you see
a limited
Aim strategy lead to deterrence failure.
You remember my point when I talked about
the military variable was that
blitzkrieg produces deterrence failures,
attrition strategy, deterrence, success,
limited aim, strategy,
most of the time deterrence, success.
What I'm telling you is
when you factor in the political variable
and there are intense pressures
to go to war and then
the state, if
it doesn't have the capability to launch
a blitzkrieg,
will launch a limited Aim strategy.
And let me give you what I think
are the two classic examples of that.
One is the 1973 Egyptian attack
against the Israelis in the Sinai.
The Egyptians crossed the Suez Canal,
and they grabbed off a piece of territory
in the Sinai
that Israel had controlled up till then,
and then they shifted to the defensive.
It was a clear, limited aim strategy.
Now, why did the Egyptians do that?
On March 8th,
who was then the president of Egypt, felt
that it was absolutely essential
that the Egyptians use military force
against Israel to send a clear message
to Israel that they had they,
meaning the Egyptians had to get back
the Sinai Peninsula.
So they launched in October of 1973.
This limited aims strategy.
They did not launch a blitzkrieg
because there was no way
that the Egyptians could defeat
the Israelis with a blitzkrieg strategy
that was off the table,
and they did not want to engage
in attrition war if they could avoid it.
So they launched a limited Aim strategy.
Same is true with the Japanese.
When they attacked
the United States at Pearl Harbor
in December of 1941,
it was a limited aim strategy.
The Japanese understood full
well that they could not defeat
the United States decisively.
They did not have a strategy
that would produce decisive victory,
but nevertheless,
the Japanese felt that they were compelled
to attack the United States because
the United States was strangling them
economically, and they had to figure a way
to get out of this
incredibly difficult situation
that they were in.
The United States
would not negotiate with them.
So they decided to launch a war.
And again,
they did not have a blitzkrieg strategy.
They wanted to avoid a war of attrition.
So they launched a limited Aim strategy,
which is what the Pearl
Harbor attack was all about.
So you see, in the case of Egypt and 73
and the Japanese in 1941,
two instances of a state
actually pursuing a limited Aim strategy,
two cases where deterrence broke down
because the attacking forces adopted
the limit, adopted a limited Aim strategy.
But the only reason you got a limited
Aim strategy in those two cases
was because the political forces pushing
each one of those states to go to war
were just so incredibly powerful.
But otherwise, as I say, the key
to understanding whether or not deterrence
fails is whether or not a state
that's contemplating war
has a blitzkrieg strategy
available or not.
In other words, whether it can win
a quick and decisive victory.
So this is basically my theory
of conventional deterrence.
Now, what I want to do is switch
gears, and I want to talk
about the Russian decision
to invade Ukraine on February 24th, 2022.
And of course, my argument
is that the Russians
could choose among three strategies.
They could choose a blitzkrieg,
they could choose an attrition
strategy, or they could choose a limited
aim strategy.
Maybe I shouldn't say they could choose.
They could contemplate.
It's probably a better way to put it.
They could contemplate
a blitzkrieg strategy,
an attrition strategy,
or a limited aim strategy.
Now, the conventional wisdom in the West
is that the Russians
launched a blitzkrieg.
Let me say a bit more about this.
The conventional wisdom in
the West is clearly that
Vladimir Putin was an aggressor
who was interested
in conquering all of Ukraine
and incorporating it
into a Greater Russia.
And of course, as you know,
many people believe that
after he was done with Ukraine,
he would try to conquer
other territory in Eastern Europe
and reestablish the Soviet empire.
But that's all beside the point,
because we're simply concerned here
about the question
of why Russia attacked Ukraine.
And again, the goal
so the conventional wisdom goes,
is that Putin wanted to conquer
all of Ukraine.
This is another way of saying that Putin
was pursuing a decisive victory.
And of course, he thought he was going
to win a quick and decisive victory.
He thought that he had this formidable
military instrument,
the Russian army,
that would quickly overrun
the Ukrainian army and up
conquering all of Ukraine
and then incorporating it
into a Greater Russia.
This would be a quick
and decisive victory.
And of course, as I said to you,
when I laid out my theory
that if a state thinks
that it can affect the blitzkrieg,
then deterrence is going to fail.
And if you can,
if you accept the conventional wisdom
about what Putin was up to,
it's obvious why deterrence failed
and why Russia invaded Ukraine.
Now, I
disagree with this argument,
but before I tell you why,
let me note that once
the blitzkrieg failed
and of course the blitzkrieg failed
in the conventional wisdom,
what you got was a war of attrition.
And this was the point that I made to
you earlier.
Remember I said, when a blitzkrieg fails,
it leads to a war of attrition.
This is what happened to the Soviets
on the Eastern Front in World War Two.
And so the conventional wisdom goes.
This is what happened to the Russians
efforts.
They invaded Ukraine.
The blitzkrieg failed
and we got a war of attrition.
Now, why is this argument wrong?
First of all, there is no way
that the Russian army that went into
Ukraine
could have come even close
to conquering all of Ukraine.
It was just too small, the Russian army,
and it was not a high quality
military machine.
It was not an army that was well
oiled for offensive operations.
It was an army that was basically built
for a defensive mission.
And furthermore, as I said,
it was a rather small army.
I argue that the Russian army
that went into
Ukraine had at most 190,000
troops, 190,000 general
who is the head of the Ukrainian military
today, argues that the Russians went in
with 100,000 troops.
There is absolutely no way
that the Russians
could even come close
to conquering all of Ukraine
with 100,000 troops,
or even with 190,000 troops.
When the Vermont, the German Army
went into Poland in 1939.
And you want to remember that
the Vermont was only interested
in conquering the western
one half of Poland,
because the Soviet Union was going
to conquer the eastern one half of Poland.
When the Wehrmacht went into western
Poland, it had 1.5
million men, 1.5 million,
and the western half of Poland
is much smaller than Ukraine.
And again, general says the Russians
went in with 100,000 troops.
I say they win in with at most 190,000
troops.
And again,
this was not an army that was well suited
for offensive military operations.
To put it in slightly different terms,
this was not the Wehrmacht.
The Wehrmacht was a formidable
fighting force that was top notch
when it came to executing
offensive armored operations.
That was not the Russian army.
So my first argument
against the conventional wisdom,
and again, the conventional wisdom, is
that Russia was bent
on achieving
a quick and decisive victory,
is that they just didn't have an army
that was big enough to achieve that goal.
Second point I would make to you
is that one day after the offensive
started on February 25th, Dmitry Peskov,
who was at the time
Putin's principal
spokesman, reached out to the Ukrainians
and said that
the Russians were interested
in starting negotiations.
Just think about this.
One day after the Russians start the war,
the Russians reach out to the Ukrainians
and say they'd like to start negotiations
to put an end to the war.
This does not fit with the story
that Putin was bent on conquering
all of Ukraine and incorporating it
in to a greater Russia.
Then what happens over
the course of March?
This is March 2022,
right after the war starts.
Is that the Ukrainians
and the Russians begin to negotiate
with each other,
and eventually what happens
is on 29th March.
On 29th March, there's a little over
one month after the war starts.
Negotiations
to end the war start in Istanbul.
These are the famous Istanbul negotiations
that are designed to shut down the war.
Furthermore, and this is very important
as a goodwill gesture,
the Russians evacuate their military
from around the key region
and they, in effect,
turn the key region over to Ukraine.
Again,
this does not sound like the Russians,
and in particular,
Vladimir Putin, were bent on conquering
all of Ukraine,
winning a decisive victory.
And in fact,
what happens after 19th March in Istanbul
is that the two sides
do begin to negotiate, and it's very clear
that there are a lot
of difficult issues on the table,
and it's not clear
you would have ever gotten an agreement.
But the central agreement on the table
is the question of Ukrainian neutrality.
And what was going on here
is that the Russians just wanted
to make sure
that Ukraine did not join NATO.
They were not interested
in conquering all of Ukraine.
They did walk, did not want Ukraine
to turn into a Western bulwark
on that on their border.
And that's what
this operation was all about.
I'll talk more about this in a second.
But the point I'm trying to make to you
is that given
the size of the Russian army,
given the quality of the Russian army,
and given the fact that the Russians
reach out to the Ukrainians
to start negotiations right after the war
starts, and then given the fact that
those negotiations actually started
a little over a month later,
it's, in my opinion, almost impossible
to sustain the story
that the Russians were interested
in conquering Ukraine.
My final point on this is those
negotiations eventually break down.
And as I said,
I'm not sure that they ever would have
produced a final agreement
that would have ended the war back then.
But it's not the Russians
who walk away from the negotiations.
I think it's the Ukrainians
who bear the principal responsibility
from walking away from the negotiations.
And of course, what happens then?
What's
what's the war is not settled in Istanbul,
is it evolves into a war of attrition.
Okay.
Let me give you my view, using my theory
on what happened
that led to the war on February
24th, 2022,
the Russians did not launch a blitzkrieg.
I've just tried to give you some evidence.
There's more, but I gave you
some of the principal evidence
that shows you
this was not a case of Vladimir Putin
turning his army loose to conquer
all of Ukraine.
Know what Putin did is he launched
the limited Aim strategy.
If you go into Ukraine with 100,000
or 190,000 troops and you withdraw
from Kyiv as soon as the negotiations
in Istanbul starts,
you're pursuing a limited
Aim strategy here.
What Putin did was Putin went into Ukraine
and he captured a small chunk,
a small chunk of territory
inside of Ukraine.
And he then told
the Ukrainians
that he wanted to start negotiating.
What's going on here?
What's going on here is that Putin
believed that NATO's policy
of trying to incorporate Ukraine
into the Western alliance,
the West policy of trying
to make Ukraine a western bulwark
on Russia's
border, was an existential threat.
The Russians were perfectly clear
on this issue
from April 8th,
excuse me, from April 2008 forward.
And of course, April 2008 is
when NATO says that Ukraine
will become part of the alliance
from April 2008 forward.
The Russians are clear this is an existential threat, and it's not going to happen
in December of 2021,
January of 2022 and in February of 2022.
These are the three months before the war
starts.
The Russians go to enormous lengths to try
to negotiate with the West to avoid a war.
The Russians are not interested in war.
This is perfectly clear.
If you look at the historical record for
those three months before the war started.
Nevertheless,
the West has zero interest in negotiating
with the Russians to make sure
that a war does not break out over
Ukraine.
Just go look at the historical record.
You'll find hardly
any evidence that the West,
which believe
that the Russians might attack.
You want to understand
that many people in the West thought
that there was a good chance
that the Russians would attack.
Nevertheless,
the West and here I'm talking
mainly about the United States,
did virtually nothing to prevent a war.
What this
meant was that Putin was desperate.
He believed that he faced, well,
I should say his country
faced an existential threat.
And he had to deal
with this existential threat.
He fully understand, fully understood
that he had no blitzkrieg option.
That was not in the cards.
Putin was not
Putin was not running the Vermont.
The Russian army was not the Vermont.
The Russian Army was a defensively
oriented army, small in number.
It had no capability
of winning a decisive victory in Ukraine.
So he pursued a limited aim strategy.
This is exactly
what my theory would predict.
The political variable here,
the political forces
that were pushing Putin to go to war
were extremely powerful.
Again, Putin felt
that Russia faced an existential threat.
He had to deal with that threat.
And the United States
and the Europeans were doing
nothing to negotiate a way to avoid war.
So he felt he had to use military force.
And as I've said,
he had no blitzkrieg option.
So what he did
was he launched a limited Aim strategy.
And if you look at the size of the Army,
and if you look at his interest
in sending a signal to the Ukrainians
to, let's start negotiating
right after the war starts,
you see clearly that
this is what he had in mind.
However, as I told you
at the beginning of the lecture,
the problem of the limited aim strategy
is that the other side,
the target state, is unlikely
to roll over and play dead.
It's unlikely to surrender, and indeed
it's likely to continue the fight.
And in this case, Ukraine,
with help from the West.
This includes the Europeans
and the United States.
And we're talking about, with abundant
help from the West,
the Ukrainians continue
the fight against Russia.
I believe that
one of the principal reasons
that the Ukrainians walk away
from the Istanbul negotiations,
and I believe that the West encourages
them to do that.
To do
this is because they believe that Ukraine,
with help from the West,
can prevail over the Russians
in the long term because the Russian army
is not that strong,
which, of course, is why
it pursued a limited Aim strategy.
So the Ukrainians,
with help from the West, continue the war.
And what's the end result?
The end result is that this limited aim
strategy turns into a war of attrition.
And of course, as all the viewers know,
we are now
engaged in a war of attrition with Russia
on one side, Ukraine
and the West on the other side.
So to sum up here,
when you think about what happened
on February 24th, 2022,
what you want to do
is think about this as a case of a failure
of conventional deterrence.
And as I said before, when you think
about conventional deterrence,
you have to think about the political
variable and the military variable.
And when you think
about the military variable,
there are three strategies blitzkrieg,
attrition, and limited aim strategy.
And if a potential attacker can pursue
a blitzkrieg
strategy, deterrence is likely to fail.
And the only time
I think you're going to get a state
pursuing a limited Aim strategy,
which is the second best alternative,
but not a great alternative,
is when the political forces
that call for war are so powerful
that a state is willing to risk it
and pursue a limited Aim strategy.
And I think what happened
in the case of the Ukraine war
is that the Russians
did not have a blitzkrieg strategy.
I know that's the conventional wisdom, but
they did not have a blitzkrieg strategy.
They pursued a limited aim strategy.
And the reason they pursued limited
Aim strategy is
because they thought
that they faced an existential threat,
that they had to deal with that threat,
and they could not deal with the threat
through negotiations
with the West,
because the West would just not negotiate.
So they had to use military force.
And they launched this limited attack
on February
24th, 2022, which at first began
to look like it might work.
You want to remember you got negotiations
at Istanbul, and there are many people
who do think there was a good chance
those negotiations would have worked
had the West not encouraged
the Ukrainians to walk away.
But the negotiations failed,
and here we are
in this lengthy war of attrition.
And as I said, this is exactly
what my argument would expect.
So that's my story on
the origins and also on the
conduct of
the Ukraine war since February 24th, 2022.
Thank you very much for your attention.